Shand side welcome to concept and coding
and today we are going to start with
rest clients and we will understand it
totally in depth but this is the
prerequisite video rest template if you
have any doubt regarding with this topic
because that's where we have created the
fundamentals right so first have a look
at this then understanding rest client
would be little easy okay so if you
remember in the previous video we know
what are the limitations of rest
template. So one of the biggest you can
say that the limitation is so many
overloaded methods. It is very difficult
to remember and maintain and that's what
one of the advantage of restclines is
that we are going to avoid these many
overloaded
methods. But let's see what are the
other alternatives of rest templates. So
we can say that there are two
alternative one is web client another is
rest client. So here if you see the web
client is a asynchronous non-blocking in
nature means client do not wait for the
response from the server before
continuing. So this is used in reactive
programming generally when we will learn
about spring web flux I will cover web
client into that one but generally we
are covering synchronous communication
right. So rest
client is a synchronous blocking in
nature like like a rest template. So
means client wait for the response from
the server before continuing. Okay. And
it is introduced in spring framework 6
plus and spring boot 3 plus. Okay. So
you can say that this is a modern
fluentbased API that is more readable
and easy to maintain. Okay. And this is
more frequently used
than rest
template. We will see why.
Okay. Now we have used one word fluent
based
API. What is that? Very very important.
We need to understand this. Then only we
would be able to get how rest actually
works. Otherwise we might have to do lot
of remembering thing like okay now which
method I have to use. Okay
so let's start with first very basic
example let's say that if order service
has to invoke product service what has
to be done in rest line. Okay then we
will see that like okay once it is done
how exactly it is working. So we have a
order service which is running on
localhost
8081 and the product service I am
running it on different port
8082. Now this is the first part in the
app config I am creating an object of
restclient. So I am creating restclient
dot create. Internally it is calling uh
restclient dot
builder dot build.
So internally it does this or you can
even itself call
restclient.builder.build. Okay. So this
will create you a new object of
restclient. It will give you a new
object of rest client. Okay. So that is
the first step we have done. Get an
object of the rest
client. So in the second I have written
very simple controller like we have seen
in the rest template also. Okay. So I
have uh written one API/order / id and
this is my get method. So here I am
using this restclient object which is
created. Okay. So I'm autoiring it here.
Rest client. Now see this rest client
dot get dot URI which the exact URI
which I want to hit or which I want to
invoke dot retrieve dot body. This is
the body I wanted for my response
string.class. So that's why I'm
retrieving it in string
only. And here if you see I am just
printing out system dot dot print ln
response from product API which is
called from order service. And whatever
the response this is sending is this
one and output is order call successful.
Now when I hit in the post band, okay, I
called this / order /1 /order /
one. So order call is successful and in
the
logs it should print this response from
product API call from order service and
this is what I got from
the product service what it return
string. So here if you
see this is the template which we are
going to use for all different operation
like post, put, delete. But here if you
see its structure it's fluent. So what
is fluent? Now you can ask one question.
Hey you are saying fluent. This is
fluent API. What exactly fluent API
means? So see understand this one.
Fluent API
means Fluent API
means chaining of
methods. Chaining of
methods. So what generally happen is you
have method one. Method one it is
returning an
object. It is returning an
object which opens up different set of
method. Let's say method two, method
three, method four. Okay. So first you
call method one. Method one returns you
an
object which has
this methods. You can now call any of
this method. Okay. Now this
method might return you different
object which opens up different set of
methods.
So what we are doing is we are doing
chaining. From method
one we got some
object which opens up different set of
methods. So I from method one I reach to
method four. From method four I reach to
method six. From method six I reach to
some method 8. Something like that. So
there is a chaining of
method. Okay. So that's what we are
doing here. We are doing a chaining of
method. So these methods like dot get
dot uri dot retrieve dot body they might
not be present into just one class. Okay
let's say this is class one this is
class 2 this is class 3 this is class 4.
So all these methods could be present
into different different classes itself.
But the chaining is happening when I did
dot get it return me some
object right different different class
object which has this URI method. This
dot URI might return me some object of
totally different class which has this
retrieve. Now this retrieve again in
turn return me an object which has
totally different which belongs to
totally different class. this object and
which has the body method. So you got
it. I am doing a method
chaining and this method might be
present into different different
methods. Okay. So that is known as
fluent
API. I will show you how we are
achieving this so that we don't have to
uh mug up this thing that okay first I
have to use get then I have to use URI
then I have to use retrieve or what is
the purpose of using the retrieve? Why I
have to keep body at last? Right?
Because sequence
matters, right? In the chaining because
when we are saying chaining, the chain
should not break. The chain should not
break. If I directly call this method
m_sub_2 of class 2, it returning me an
object of let's say this object it
return me an object of this class. So I
can only goes to now m class 3 only. I
can't now move back to class one this
method one. So chain will get
break. Okay. So sequence meth matters in
the chaining of methods and in the
fluent
API. Okay. And this is just an example
for get no matter we are going to use
post put delete we are going to follow
the same
template. We don't have to remember
different different method overloaded
methods which is there in the rest
template.
Okay, so that's what I told you. What
does fluent API means? Fluent API means
chaining of method
calls. Each call, each method call
returns an object of next step. Okay,
that expose next set of
operations. I have already explained
what when we say when I say fluent API
what exactly it means.
So now our next doubt is how this
chaining works in rest client. So that
we understand better how
this dot get dot uri dot
header dot after that retrieve then dot
body will work. how it's working like
this sequence is right but I don't have
to remember it right so how to grabs
the like base so that we don't have to
remember that okay hey can I use header
before URI or what if URI I can use
after retrieve is it possible does
chaining break or not so let's see this
class diagrams
So this class diagram you can say that
this is the start of chain
first this is the start of chain rest
line. So in the first step we are
already creating a object of rest line
right once we get the object of rest
client then we have different methods
right we can invoke get post put delete
okay then this is the
second so here if you see these has many
interfaces URI spec which expose methods
related to setting the URI either you
can give me a string or You can create a
URI builder itself and then return with
the
URI. Okay. Then you have one interface
for request header
respect which has various method to set
the headers and
cookies. Then we have one interface
which is child of both URI spec. So it
extends URI spec and request header
spec. Similarly, we have one uh
interface for body. So during post and
put we need to set the content type,
content length, body, right? So this
interface expose those
methods. Then there is an interface
which is a child of both like uh request
header URI. It's a child of request
header URI and the request body spec.
And then there is one implementation
method default request body URI spec. So
it it's an implementation of this which
ultimately provide implementation for
all of these abstract methods. It all it
provide the implementation for all of
this. So you can say that this is
ultimately the
request no matter whether if you are
creating get then also this object has
to be created. If you are building post
or put or delete, no matter what
operation you are doing, we have to
create an object of this. And forget, we
might have to fill up some operation.
For post, we might have to fill up some
fields like I need to fill up the
body. So now the only thing is how to
fill up this. But one thing is second
step is we have to create an object of
this. But we have to do
chaining like first I have to set URI
then I can set headers then I can set
body then what
next. Okay so request buildup and also
if you see this is the third part
where we have something called response
spec. Okay response spec actually knows
how to handle the response.
So once we get a response from the
server we have to do its
mapping like I have to map whatever the
object I'm getting I have to map it to
string or I have mapped I have to map it
to this
object okay and also if there is an
exception how to do
an exception
handling like if a status is 4xx how
what to do if a status is 5xx what to
do. So this interface response spec
has support us like on status. So this
is used for exception
handling. Okay. And here if you see it
has a method like to entity to uh body
which ultimately helps in like
uh calling the execute method or you can
say that actual internally it actually
invoke the
method which is responsible for creating
TCP connection sending HTTP request
getting the response. Okay. And after
that
this interface and this concrete class
itself help us in what once the response
we get back how to handle the response.
We'll see that. But this is a very high
level I'm telling
you these are the classes which we are
going to
use in our get put post operation. But
now we just need to see how the chaining
works.
Okay. So first thing first you need to
know a little bit about generic class
and wild card in Java which I have
already covered in the Java series.
Okay. So here if you see there are lot
of uh generic types we are using. We are
using wild card we are using generic
types right. So you should not get
confused that what exactly and how it is
working. So now let's start with
the get operation.
So here the first thing which we are
doing is creating an object of rest
line. So either you can do dot create or
you can do dot builder dot build
right. Okay. So internally create also
does the same thing only. Okay.
So objective here is first get an object
of rest line. Now once we get an object
of rest client what I am doing now see
the chaining the first I am calling dot
get method. So here if you go into the
restclient
interface okay when you invoke a
get it creates an object of this class
default request body ur. So as I told
you that ultimately we have to create an
object of this because it has all the
fields which is required to make a TCP
connection to send HTTP request and the
response also how to handle the
response. So ultimately this object we
have to create. So during get it creates
an object of default request body URI
spare and set it HTTP method to get.
Okay. And what is the return type it is
returning? It is returning request
header URI specs. The next object. Okay.
So I am creating an object of this. See.
So this
object it's a child of request body URI
spec which is again a child of request
header URI spec which is I am returning.
So it's a valid return type even though
I'm creating an object of this and
returning this but the return type I can
write this okay because this is a parent
of this
one. So from the get I am done. This
returns me an object of request header
URI spec. Okay. So now I am
here from this I have see this is a
child of two interfaces means I can
invoke from here I can invoke the method
of this interface and this interface.
Okay. So now next set of operations got
open. So currently I am going and
invoking dot URI. So also see the how
sequencing matter the chain should not
break. Okay, I will also show you one of
the flow where the chain breaks also. So
from here request header URI spec I
decided to invoke the
URI
method.
Okay. Okay. Since this URI interface
which one is the implementation the same
one we have already created an object in
the uh step one. So this URI it will
fill up this URI. So I invoke this
method URI and pass the string. So
internally it will create a
URI object of this using some URI
builder and set this field into this
object. Now what its return type? Its
return type is
this any
child or even this class itself. So s
extend. So what does it mean? s
extends and let's say class name. So
this mean that the return type or here
what what the type here is the type here
could be
any either this class this class name a
let's say any class which is child of
this class name a or this itself so
either this class name a itself or any
child of it. So child one child two
child three. So here I can get
either class name A or C1 child one or
child two or child three all are
valid okay that's what because I am
bounding the limit of the type what I
can get here in the URI spec what I can
get here either I can get this type or
its child type so either I can get this
type request header spec or it's any of
its
child. Okay. So
now
since I don't know what child it is
because request header spec which is
this request header spec it has many
child. So this is child one. This is
child two. This is child three. It could
be many childs right? I don't know
specifically which child it is
corresponding to because here I'm
sending wild card. So I don't know
because the same wild card is passed to
here. Same wild card is passed to here.
So I don't know which child I am
referring to. So it uses by default the
parent. Okay. So now I do URI return me
an object of the
next class or interface which is request
header spec. So s is now request header
spec. So now I am calling accept method.
So it is calling the accept method on
this
interface and it has its implementation
might be provided here. Except
implementation would be there. So it
might be setting some header. Okay. Now
what is the return type of this s here
itself? So s extends request header
spec. Again the same thing the type
could be request header spec. The same
class it is now calling to its same
itself or it's any of its child. But
since we don't know what child it is
either child one, child two or child
three. The by default it is pointing to
itself request header respect. So for
the except method return type it's
itself. Okay. So you are getting an
object but that object is the same same
class
itself. Now here I am calling more
methods like dot header. So I am also
able to set the header. So I'm calling
invoking a method which is present in
now the same
class. So this header also return type
is s which is again it's of same type
same class type. Okay. So from header I
also get
a return object which is again of a same
type. So I'm able to call the method
retrieve which is also present into the
same class. So retrieve is also present
here in this itself. So I invoke
retrieve. Now the when I call retrieve
its return type is different. Now means
it is returning me an object of some
different
class. Okay. So what it does? So
retrieve creates an object of this
response
spec. So default response spec is an
implementation of this. So it create an
object and return me this. So I'm
getting an object of response spec
now. So I'm getting an object of
response specs means I am getting a new
object which has different set of
methods. Now I can
call methods which are present into the
objects which this retrieve has
returned. So I got a response spec
object. So from there I called the body.
So I called
the body. So its implementation is
present here.
So this body
internally calls the
method which actually does the work of
creating a TCP connection and sending
this. So here it invokes the exchange
method and exchange method is again
present into this header spec. Okay. So
it is calling this
one. Okay. So the reason why we come
from request header respect to this
response respect because in the
body before we calling this exchange
method which actually handles create a
TCP connection send the request get the
response we are passing this functional
interface implementation here like how
to how to do the mapping
of
response. How
to handle the exception. We provide the
implementation of this functional
interface and then call this and this
here it provide an implementation of
exchange where ultimately it goes ahead
and create a TCP connection send a
request and get a response.
So here if you see the flow become
complete but I will also show you like
if we don't follow the sequence how the
flow breaks. Okay, don't worry about
first of all don't worry about if you
don't understand response respect
clearly if you don't understand how this
connection is happening how this
exchange work currently I want you to
focus on the flow how this understand
fluent API what is fluent API so even
though we are calling this sequence of
methods how exactly it moves from one
class to different class then another to
different class okay so chaining of
methods which are present into different
different
classes. Okay. So see can a flow be
broken if you don't follow a sequence.
Let's see that I create an object of the
rest client. I do restclient dot get.
When I did a get you know that what
happened? It will create me an object of
this and it will
set the HTTP method
get and return me an object of request
header URI spec which is a valid even
though I'm returning this object because
this is ultimately a child of this only.
So it's a valid return
type. So now I got an
object. So I am here now. So from this I
have an option to call URI or this
methods because this class it's a child
of both. It's a child of both.
So now instead of calling URI I decided
to call the except. So now I am calling
this
except. So what except will do except uh
set the header. It's inside a header. It
will set except
application/json header and value. Okay.
But what its return type?
return type is S which
is either request header spec which is
the same class or any of its child since
we don't know which child it is child
one child two child three because
currently it is coming as from here it
is coming as question mark wild card and
the same we have passed here okay so it
is coming as a wild card but we know
that either it's a request header
respect or any of its child but since we
don't know the exact child it's always
safe to treat it as the same parent
only. Okay. So it is now returning an
object of itself request header
respect. So this returning an object of
the same request header respect. So now
can you call URI now? No. because this
is a total different uh interface which
has this URI method and it is now not
present into request header
spec now the chain is broken you can't
set the URI so means you you can't even
send the request because URI is not
itself set so you have to follow a
proper sequence that uh from method one
I goes to method two from method two I
goes to method three like this and the
chain complete
Got it? So similarly let's see a post
and while we reach till the delete right
this whole diagram will get clear to you
for sure.
Okay. So first thing first creating an
object of rest
client. Now first thing I'm doing is
calling post. So now restclient has post
method. The same post will do creating
an object of this and sending the HTTP
method to post and it returns this
object default request. So here what is
the return type? Request body URI spec
is it valid? So this default request
body URI is a child of request body URI
spec. Request body URI spec we are
sending. So it's a valid. So I'm sending
it this its parent only. Okay. So I
created an object of this but return
type I put it as this and it's a valid
because it's a parent of this
one. Okay. So now I reach till this
point from this point it's a child of uh
so this is its parent one this is parent
two interfaces right so I can invoke
methods which is here invoke method
which is
here and which is again a child of uh
this class and this class. So means from
this point I can invoke any
method either URI either accept header
retrieve exchange body any method
because this class is a child of
all. So what I did I call the URI
because chaining matters I don't want to
break the chain. If I call except I
can't move back to
URI because nobody is returning me an
object of URI spec again.
So that's why from here I call
the URI. So URI will set me the URL and
what its return type. Now understand
that what would be the return type. So
here if you
see it is a child of request header URI
spec and what is the type it is passing
request body spec. Okay. So now this
will translate
to request
body spec which is this one. Okay. And
is it fulfilling this either child
either parent request respect or any of
its child. So here this is parent or any
of its child. So this is its child this
is child. So I'm putting one of its
child only.
request body specs is child of this
only. So it's a valid
one. Okay. And in the URI spec I'm
passing this what I'm getting. So here
itself this get translated
to request body spec and ultimately this
s itself is request body spec object. So
means I reach till this point.
Now sorry. So now in the URI return me
an object of request body
spec
which has its own methods to set the
body. Okay. Set the body, set the
content type, content length. It has
many methods. So now we can invoke that
and also we can invoke its parent. We
can also invoke its parent except header
retrieve. So I am calling the its parent
method
except I'm calling its parent method
except so it will set the header but
what would be its return type? Its
return type is s. So here if you see
this request body spec extend the parent
and pass what is the type? This itself.
So this type
is translate to request
body spec itself and this s it s get
translated to this request body spec
means this class
itself. So means this return type is
this object itself. So I will reach to
this point itself again. So after accept
I got an object of request body spec
itself. From there I decided again to
call the parent which it return me an S
which is again object of request body
spec
itself. Then I call the body method
which is present inside
this sorry which which is present inside
this. I set the body because during post
operation let's say I want to create a
new operation. I set the
body. Okay. And it returns me same
object. Now from there I call the
retrieve because still I can call the
parent mode. Right? So I call the
retrieve. So I reach till this point
now. So from retrieve what it will do is
it will get me an object of default
response back. It will create me an
object of
this which is used to uh to handle the
response and it returns me this response
respect. So now this return me an object
of different class response
respect and then I call the two entity
of that one. So I call the response
respect two entity. So two entity if you
see
that it will internally invoke the
exchange method which is present inside
this header itself and this exchange
implementation is present here in its
implementation and all the request is
already properly filled up headers and
all. So it knows how to make a
connection. What it is coming from here
is I already told you that we call this
exchange method. But in the exchange
function we tell we this is a uh lambda
expression. We pass the
functionality how to handle
response, how to handle status or
exception handling and do I need to
close the connection response connection
or not? True
false. So that info come from this and
your flow get completes. So at this
point of time internally it calls this
exchange method which create TCP
connection send request get response do
mapping and give us the
response. Similarly delete. So you can
go through delete by yourself right but
now you will get the flow. What till
this point my aim is that you understand
what is fluent
API and how rest client adhere to this
framework of fluent API from one method
to another which belongs to different
class and these are the classes involved
in the rest API delete is also very same
like first goes to delete it create me
an object of this then it will return
header URI spec so I come here then I
call URI
from URI it would be like so it's a
question mark right so I don't know
which exact child so I can't go to this
or this so that's why I go to parent so
it called retrieve it get me an object
of response from
response I ultimately invoke this two
bodyless entity because in delete you
don't uh receive body and send body okay
then ultimately internally it invokes
this exchange method method and I pass
the this functional interface expression
here itself. We will show show we will
see that. But I hope the fluent API is
clear. If anybody asks you in future is
rest API is
fluent.
Yes. How? Now I believe you should be
able to tell how what classes involves
and how these classes are actually
linked together to make the rest API
fluid.
Sorry if I stretched a bit but it is
very important to understand the fluent
API. Now let's go and see exception
handling. So now I'm very going very
specific going inside this response
spec.
Okay. So see this
one I am creating a controller. So I
have written I want to do a get call dot
get. I specify the URI the endpoint
which I want to hit when I call dot
retrieve. Now we know that when we call
retrieve we get an object of response
spec. Okay.
So it creates so we have a constructor
in this constructor it set this object
request header spec because from here
itself we are invoking from request
header spec if you remember the diagram
from request header spec itself we are
calling the
retrieve okay so it has the reference so
this gets
set okay but now I got an object of the
response spec
Now till now nothing happened. So the
even though the name said retrieve I am
not retrieving the response. I am not
hitting the client uh server. I am not
getting the actual response. It is just
giving me the response object. That's
all. Nothing much till now. Response
object means this response spec
object. Now I am filling it up. First I
am telling it on status. I am telling it
that once you get a response in future
how you should handle the
exception. So I'm calling it on status
method and it has a response error
handler which has this. So response
error handler is a functional uh
interface which has this method has
error. It's it has only one abstract
method has error which accept response.
So I am providing its lambda expression
response. If response is 4x
means some invalid input request then
I'm just saying my custom exception
throw
this else if if response is
5xx something wrong at the server side
itself there. Okay, so it's an internal
server or uh just put internal server
error. Okay, we don't know what
exception
come. Okay, otherwise return false has
error. No, no error. Okay. So this
implementation so this
implementation I passed into this
handler and now this when this on status
get invoked after retrieve I get an
object of response spec from this
response spec I called on status. So it
update the status handler this
field. Okay. So with this info whatever
the info I provided here that if for
access this implementation this
implementation ultimately gets set into
this status
handler. Okay. And after that it will
return me an object. So what object on
status is returning? On status is
returning where it is on status is
returning with the same response spec
itself. So I am whatever the object
which I'm getting it is like body is
itself the same. So I'm getting the
response spec object itself. Then I
invoke the
body. Now in the body if you see what
happened just see little bit uh more
concentration here. So in body I tell
whatever the response I get I need to
map to string. Okay. So now here if you
see the body in the
body what exactly happen
is it calls execute and extract which
internally call this exchange
method. But what I am
passing here I am passing it
this when I called exchange it has it
required this exchange function.
this exchange function I am providing
here actually it is the framework which
is providing request response read body
okay how you should once you get a
response how you should handle it so
here if you see this read
body has like message converter like
whatever the first you handle
the status handler we have already had
uh set the status handler right if
status is four access throw this
exception if it is five access throw
this exception else false move ahead and
after that it will go and whatever the
response I get it will convert to its
this
type string dotclass it will do
mapping it will do mapping to
this so all this logic I provided into
this lambda
expression this
function okay so once now at this point
of time I will call TCP HTTP request and
once I get the response ultimately then
it will execute this function. We'll see
that. Okay. So on status is used for
handling the exception and this is way
how we can handle the
exception. So if you want full control
over response building. So someone says
that hey why I have to call from here?
Why I have to do retrieve? Why my
control first go to here and from again
I have to come to this okay why I since
when I am in this
method okay I added the accept I added
the header instead of calling retrieve
can I directly call exchange and I I
will provide the my implementation that
how the response should be handled yeah
you can do that that's what I am doing
it here so I did the at it returned me
an object. From there I called the URI.
URI returned me an object. From there I
called the dot exchange
itself. Okay. Because after URI I reach
to this point. I reach to this point.
After URI I reach to this point. From
there I directly call exchange. I don't
call retrieve now because retrieve only
helps me in providing this
implementation. Right? This
implementation. this
implementation okay retrieve only help
me getting this implementation so I'm
providing my uh since this is a function
interface I'm providing my
implementation here so request response
if response is 4xx do this if it is 5xs
do this else this is how you should map
the response which once you will get
from the server so whatever the response
dot get body I am currently doing
mapping to string I'm read I'm from the
stream I am copying it to string
object okay now you don't
need this response spec now you don't
need response spec
methods you don't want on status you
don't want body you don't want two
entity you don't want anything
because you have already passed
the exchange function like how you
should handle the
response.
Okay. Now let's see a little bit inside
into the exchange method. So once we
call the exchange either by directly us
or this response it spec itself
internally when we call dot body or dot2
entity internally it call exchange
method of this one it call exchange
method of this one
right so let's
see its implementation so this is the
implementation of exchange Okay. So this
is the first
step where it create a
request. Okay. This is the place where
it actually creates a object
of HTTP
client and remember that in rest client
this HTTP client is different than in
HTTP
1.1. Okay, this is different
object. I will show you. So this is the
first. So here if you see second is
calling
execute. This is where internally it
calls uh create TCP correction send
request get
response and once you get the response
we have to do the mapping. So here it is
calling exchange function dot exchange.
So we are running the exchange function.
So whatever the functions we were
passing here right we saw that this
exchange function this
one this is exchange function okay and
uh
here we are passing this exchange
function if we are using this response
spec which tells us how to map the
response and how to handle the
exception. So this is running at the
third step. Once you get the response,
it will run the exchange
function. So first it is calling the
create
request which it
returns which it calls this default
factory which is JDK client HTTP request
factory. This is in the rest line. This
is the default. It will create an object
of HTTP
client. Again this HTTP client is
different than what we use in HTTP 1 uh
HTTP 1.1 version. This HTTP client is
present inside this package
java.net.http
HTTP and this HTTP
client supports takes care of everything
TCP connection
caching your sending
request
response right it takes care of
everything also this HTTP uh client has
support
for HTTP version 1.1 and HTTP version
two. Remember that rest
template can only handle 1.0 and 1.1. It
can handle till
two. If you remember HTTP version two
can send client server can send multiple
concurrent request HTTP request and the
server can concurrently send the
response. But in 1.1 it's always like
request response request
response. So if you want HTTP version
two you have to use the rest client
because this latest HTTP client object
provides support for
that. Okay. So it creates an object of
HTTP client returns it. Okay. After that
it will call the execute method. This
execute
method internally calls the send a sing.
Okay. So we have already created an
object of HTTP client. So using that it
calls the send a
sync. Even though it's a send a sync
it's not actually rest client is a
synchronous. So it actually wait for the
response. It here it do wait it wait for
the rest it to finish. So I told you
this HTTP client internally takes care
of connection caching support provide
support sending request getting the
response and ultimately it give us the
response. Now once we get the
response it calls the third exchange
function. Exchange function you know
that which now know how to handle the
response. So here we have created one
exchange function.
How if error comes how to handle it? If
this exception come throw this
exception. If this exception comes throw
this error. So
otherwise how to map the body either in
a string or either map to some different
object. So all this logic present inside
this here which now executed at this
point of
time.
Okay. So this is the highle flow for
it. Now one more thing is if you see
interceptor work is also very simple
into the rest client. So I have an order
service product service. Now if I have
to add an interceptor first what I have
did is I have created an interceptor my
custom request interceptor and implement
the client HTTP request interceptor. H
you have to implement this one. Now you
have to provide an implementation of
this method. So what I have to do
is whatever the request I have I am
fetching its header. Now I am
adding certain more data. So I'm
intercepting the request and adding
appending some value. So I have appended
one
header
and proceed the execution
now. Okay. So it provide me all the
methods. I have to just say that okay I
have intercepted it. I have done
whatever. Now you go ahead and
execute. Okay. So that is the first
thing we have to do. And the second
while creating a restclient instance
right we can call dobuilder.build.
build. So there we can set the
interceptor. So this is our interceptor
which we have created. So I have created
an object of my interceptor here and I
have set it here. So while creating an
object of rest client, we can set an
interceptor and that's all. So this is
as it is what we have written before. I
have a rest line. I did dot get dot URI
dot retrieve to entity and that's all.
Ultimately if you see when the control
comes here invoke it it has the header X
custom header my value whatever I have
intercepted and
set. Okay. And if the question coming to
your mind that at what place in this uh
so we have an exchange right we have
seen step one step two and step three in
what exact place this interception
catch. So if you see when we do
execute this is the place where we call
TCP connection send the request receive
the response. So before calling this
method the interceptor will get
invoked. So before this method
interceptor get
invoke and after that we just uh here
interceptor got invoke we did whatever
we have to do on request after that we
have to call execute so that it can move
ahead
okay so this is all about rest line to
be honest I can understand here it is
not that simple if you're going in
I can even stick to one level higher. I
don't even I really thought multiple
times should I go into this
flow because this is not simple to
understand. There are so many
jarens generic types and all using so it
making the flow little difficult. I was
not able to decide whether I should go
or not in depth this much or I just
covered that what is fluent API and this
methods which are
available but I took a chance that uh if
I'm able to explain this clearly or not
I tried a lot to create a better
example and uh this diagram with flow I
took a chance that if I can explain this
complicated flow So with ease. So please
have a look one more
time you will get understand about
properly what is fluent API how this
flow chaining happens
works right if you want to handle the
exception handling how you can do that
right exception handling is also very
simple
okay this response spec what is its use
right how it's helping us in the mapping
response mapping and exception handling
So all these things you will try with
your hand right you will get it clear.
If you get any doubt please feel free to
comment we can discuss further right.
Okay guys thank you. Bye.